Guide to the Mon Cochran papers, 1973-2005.
Cochran, Mon papers
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Mon Cochran papers, 1973-2005.
23-13-3720
Cochran. Moncrieff
2 Cubic Feet.
Correspondence, Reports, Printed Materials, Research Materials
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Correspondence, grant files, project files, and videos pertaining to Cochran's career and his work.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Professor of Human Development, Cornell University.
Mon Cochran received a B.A. from Harvard (1964) and M.A.(1969) and Ph.D. (1973) degrees from the University of Michigan. He directed the Cornell Early Childhood Program and retired in 2008.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Correspondence, grant files, project files, and videos pertaining to Cochran's career and his work with child care and prekindergarten programs, the Cornell Early Childhood Program, the Swedish Practicum in Childhood, Family, and Social Policy Program, and the Family Matters Project.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Moncrieff, Cochran.; Moncrieff, Cochran.; Cornell University--Faculty.; Cornell University.Family Matters Project.; Cornell University.Swedish Practicum in Childhood, Family, and Social Policy.; New York State College of Human Ecology.Dept. of Human Development.; New York State College of Human Ecology.Cornell Early Childhood Program.
Subjects:
Family life education--United States.; Communication in the family--United States.; Family--Study and teaching.; Nursery schools--New York ( State)--Ithaca.; Child care--United States.; Child care--Sweden.; Education, Preschool--United States.; Day care centers--United States.
Form and Genre Terms:
Videotapes.; Motion pictures (visual works)
INFORMATION FOR USERS
SERIES LIST
Series I. Biographical - Vita, Publications
Series II. Curriculum Material
Series III. Proposals
Series IV. Programs
Series V. Films
CONTAINER LIST
- Series I. Biographical- Vita, Publications
  - Vita, 1978,1991 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Statement of Purpose; Five Year Plan- Extension Child Development Team, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - "The Development of a Community Based Delivery System for Children's Services"-paper, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Child Abuse and Neglect Research and Demonstration Project, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Prospectus for a Program of Parenting Education for Youth Program II- Working Paper, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - "Child Care, the Workplace and Family Support Services"- paper; "Child Care and the World of Work"- article; "Childrearing, Parenthood and the World of Work"- chapter, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - "The One Parent Family: Mythology, Economics and Change"-talk; "Profit-Making in Day Care: A Right or a Ripoff?", 1978 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - "Changes in the American Family: Implications for Extension"; Professional Goals; "Mental Health and the Community: A case study"-article, 1971, 1975, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Statement of Purpose; "A Comparison of Group Day Care and Family Childrearing Patterns in Sweden"- article; "The Swedish Childrearing Study"-paper, 1977, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - The Ecology of Child Care- The Impact of Day Care and Other Family Supports on Child Development- research proposal (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - "Child Development and Personal Social Networks"-article, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Conceptual Framework, Section H- Categories for Assessing the Nature and Utilization of Personal Social Networks, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Social Networks Interview, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Ecology Project- program materials; "Education, Social Conflict and Foreign Policy in South Vietnam'-article; Book reviews and article critques, 1970, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - "The Gap Between Science and Public Policy"-paper; Teaching Goals and Course-Chidbearing Contexts: Family, Community, Ideology, 1978, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Series II. Curriculum Material
  - Ecology of Human Development- Concentration, 1982-1983 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Ecology of Human Development- Concentration, 1983-1984 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - American Childcare in Global Perspective, 1997, 2005 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Series III. Proposals
  - In Support of Families: The Pilot Testing of Two Experimental Programs- by Ingerid Bo- paper for the Carnegie Corp., 1979-06 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Carnegie Corporation, 1978-1986 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Carnegie Corporation, 1990-1999 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Ford Foundation-Correspondence, 1983-1993 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Ford Foundation- The Impact of Support Systems on Families and Children, 1979-04 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Ford Foundation- Child Survival/ A Fair Start for Children, 1983-01 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Ford Foundation- Extending the Family: the Social Networks of Parents and their Children, 1986-06 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Ford Foundation- Cornell Empowerment Project- Power and Empowerment, 1986-1987 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Ford Foundation- Extending the Study of Family and Personal Social Networks, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Ford Foundation- Empowerment and Family Support: Phase Two, 1994-07 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Grant Foundation- Proposals, Correspondence, 1982-1986 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Kellogg Foundation- Proposal, Correspondence, 1977-1984 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Kettering Foundation- The Comparative Ecology of Human Development, 1977-1983 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Lilly Endowment- Comparative Ecology of Human Development, 1977-1982 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Mailman Family Foundation- Universal Prekindergarten Assessment/The Role and Functions of Higher Education Teacher Preparation Programs, 1990-2004 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Mott Foundation- Vanguard Pilot Study of Support Systems for Black and White Families in the United States, 1977-1982 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Mott Foundation- Final Report, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Robert Wood Johnson Foundation- Training and Credentialing Family Workers: Investing in Quality Family Support Programs, 1996-1999 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Spencer Foundation- The Ecology of Children's Activities in Family and Group Settings, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - The Comparative Ecology of Human Development, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Swedish Proposal (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Swedish Program- Cornell Abroad Student Papers, 1997-1998 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Swedish Program- Cornell Abroad Student Papers, 1999-2002 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Proposals- overseas, 1977-1978 (Box 1, Folder 41)
- Series IV. Programs
  - Empowering Families- Home Visiting and Building Clusters- Family Matters Project, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 42)
    Includes tape
  - Comparative Ecology of Human Development- Research proposal- Mon Cochran and Urie Bronfenbrenner, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Family Matters- Program I Manual, 1979-05 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Family Matters Project Posters and Brochure (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Family Matters- A Report to Parents, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Family Matters Project- Resource Material, 1983-1984 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Family Matters Film Discussion Guide, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Family Matters Project- Cooperative Communication Between Home and School- Workshop Series, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Family Matters Project- School Administrator's Role in Promoting Cooperative Communication Between Home and School, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Family Matters Project- Cooperative Communication between Home and School-In-Service Education Program for Elementary Teachers (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Family Matters Project- Communication for Empowerment- Facilitator's Manual of Empowering Teaching Techniques, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Empowering Families- Home Visiting and Building Clusters- Family Matters Project, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Family Matters: Evaluation of the Parental Empowerment Program- Final report to the National Institute of Education- Mon Cochran and Charles Henderson, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Evaluation of the Syracuse Family Matters Program- by Mon Cochran, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Family Matters Project- in Spanish, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Parents, Teachers and the Community: Building Partnerships for the Child- Executive Summary- by Mary Agnes Hamilton and Mon Cochran, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - New York State Family Development Credential Report on Review of Six National Family Support Training Programs- by Karen Rich and Christiann Dean, 1995-06 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Children in my Care- newsletter produced by Cornell Early Childhood Program- in English and Spanish (Box 2, Folder 6A)
  - Cornell Early Childhood Program- publicity, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Development of the Cornell Early Childhood Program by Mon Cochran, 1995-1997 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Cornell Early Childhood Program by Mon Cochran, 1997-1999, 2000 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Promising Practices- New York State Universal Prekindergarten- Expanded Edition and regular edition- by Susan Hicks, Kristi Lekies, Mon Cochran, 1999-01, 1999-06 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Foundation for Child Development- Implementing Universal Prekindergarten in New York State, 1999 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Bank Street College of Education- Study of Universal Pre-K programs in New York State, 1999-2000 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Universal Prekindergarten in New York State- A Study of Policy and Program Impacts- Mon Cochran- principle investigator, 1999-04 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Collaborating for Kids- New York State Universal Prekindergarten by Krish Lekies and Mon Cochran, 1999-2000, 2001 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - New York State Universal Prekindergarten Assessment Meeting, 2000-05 (Box 2, Folder 14A)
  - Universal Prekindergarten Study- by the Cornell Early Childhood Program, 2000 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    Spring, Summer
  - Universal Prekindergarten Study- by the Cornell Early Childhood Program, 2001, 2002 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    Spring
  - Early Child Care for Infants, Toddlers, and Preschoolers: Examining the Broader Impacts of Universal Prekindergarten- by Kristie Lekies, Emma Heitzman, 2001 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Cornell Early Childhood Program- "Supporting Legally Exempt Child Care Providers: Ideas for Two Focus Groups", 2001-09 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Odessa- Montour Central School District Universal Prekindergarten Program Study- Final Report by Susan Ariel Werner, 2001-05 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Early Childhood Workforce Preparation in New York State - pilot study- Cornell Early Childhood Program, 2002-11 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Preparing Teachers to Teach: Strenghening Early Childhood Teacher Education in New York, 2002 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - New York State School Age Credential Instructors Kit, 2003 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Middle Childhood: Meeting the Needs of 5-8 Year Olds, V-1440 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Pre-Adolescence: Meeting the Needs of 9-12 Year Olds, V-1441 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Continuing the Collaboration- Universal Prekindergarten Expansion in New York State - By Kristi Lekies and Mon Cochran, 2004 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Implementing a State-Wide Universal Prekindergarten Program: A New York City Case Study- by Fran Schwartz, 2004 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Implementing a State-Wide Universal Prekindergarten Program: An Urban Case Study- by Mon Cochran, 2004 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Implementing a State-Wide Universal Prekindergarten Program: A Rural Case Study- by Sarah Watamura, 2004 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Implementing a State-Wide Universal Prekindergarten Program: A Small City Case Study- by Sarah Watamura (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Families and Work Institute- Mind in the Making, Early Learning Modules, 2004-02 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Families and Work Institute- Learning Modules, 2004; V-1446 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Raising All Boats: Community-based Programs as Partners in Universal Prekindergarten- by Kristi Lekies, Mon Cochran, Taryn Morrissey, 2005 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Early Childhood Workforce Preparation Faculty Survey- two year colleges, 2005 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Early Childhood Workforce Preparation Faculty Survey- four year colleges and universities, 2005 (Box 2, Folder 34)
- Series V. Films
  - Family Matters - 16 mm film - 1986-04, 1970